Guide to the Ohio Company Papers, 1736-1813 DAR.1925.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- George Mason, 1750-1785; III.
  - John Tucker's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, July 17, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Jasper Sutton's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, July 27, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - John and Isaac Pearse's account with George Mason and the Ohio Company, October 4, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Jacob Hood's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, October 8, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - William Patterson's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, October 24, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Jonathan Coburn's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, October 25, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - William Castleman's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, October 28, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Frederick Ice's promise to repay George Mason and the Ohio Company, December 17, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - James Martin's debt to George Mason and the Ohio Company, March 1, 1752 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Thomas Rutherford's debt to George Mason and the Ohio Company, 1752 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Thomas Caton's debt to George Mason, 1752 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - James Martin to Gabril Jones, June 1, 1753 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Richard Pearis debt to George Mason, George Mercer and the Ohio Company, February 1757 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - George Mason to Robert Carter, January 23, 1768 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Indenture between George Mason and J. McCubbin (2 copies), July 13, 1785 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - List of jurors, George Mason v. Thomas Caton, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Robert Lemen's debt to George Mason and the Ohio Company, July 6, 1752 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - George Mason to James Mercer, January 13, 1772 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Joseph Gough's debt to George Mason, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
- George Croghan, 1745-1778; IV.
  George Croghan (ca. 1720-1782) was the Ohio Company's lead trader in Pennsylvania. Born in Ireland, he moved to the colonies in 1741 and traded with the Iroquois, from whom he claimed to have purchased 200,000 acres in 1764. Manuscripts in this series include accounts for household goods, debt notes, and documentation of land sales. Of particular interest are two copies of a 1749 advertisement for a fugitive bonded servant. See the Darlington Autograph Files (dar192507) and the Fort Pitt Wastebook (dar192503) for manuscripts related to Croghan's trade in the Ohio country.
  - John Collin's account with George Croghan, 1745 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - George Croghan and William Trent's business account, 1747-1751 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - George Croghan's business account, 1748-1749 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - James Rutlidge's account with George Croghan, 1749-1750 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Thomas Caton vs. George Croghan, 1748-1757 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Peter Demoss' account with William Trent and George Croghan, April 18, 1749 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - George Johnston's advertisement for a fugitive bonded servant (2 copies), July 1, 1749 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - George Johnston to Joseph Cambine, September 21, 1749 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Margaret Steedman's account with George Croghan, 1749 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - George Croghan to George Johnston, May 9, 1750 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - George Croghan's promise to repay Henry [Vanmeter], October 8, 1750 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Joseph Chambers vs. George Johnston, 1750 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Patrick Reilly's promise to repay William Trent and George Croghan, 1750 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Conrad Brinkner's promise to repay George Croghan, 1750 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Linhard Hellen's account with James Kelly, July 1750 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - George Croghan to Gabriel Jones, May 2, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - J. Duncan O'Gullion's debt to William Trent and George Croghan, August 15, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - B. Harrison vs. Barnard Dougherty, 1759-1765 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Fergeson Croghan's account with Felix Gilbert, 1766 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Francis Sanderson's account with John Connoley, September 19, 1775 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Sale of land by George Croghan to Michael McKewan, February 17, 1778 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Thomas Cresap, 1739-1770; V.
  Colonel Thomas Cresap (1702-1790) was a landowner and trader who settled in Maryland. In later life, he became embroiled in land disputes along the Pennsylvania border. Cresap traded goods for the Ohio Company, and materials in this series include accounts and debts for dry goods. See the Darlington Autograph Files (dar192507) for an additional manuscript relating to Cresap.
  - Richard Poulson's account with Thomas Cresap, 1739 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Debt's to Thomas Cresap, 1739-1750 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Debt of Daniel Connoly to Isaac Garrison, December 9, 1742 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Robert Paul's account with Thomas Cresap, 1744-1745 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Roger Birkham's account with Thomas Cresap, 1750 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Roger Burkham's account with Thomas Cresap, 1750 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - William Ross's account with Thomas Cresap, 1744-1749 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Patrick Matthew's account with Thomas Cresap, 1744-1755 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Thomas Cresap's account with William Ross, 1745-1750 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Judgment in Joseph Walker vs Brent Nutthall, June 25, 1745 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Job Pearsall's account with Thomas Cresap, 1746 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Noah Hampton's account with Thomas Cresap, October 1746 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Debts witnessed by Thomas Cresap, 1746-1747 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - William Biggerstaff's account with Thomas Cresap, 1747-1748 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - John Large's promise to repay John Jack, Sept 25, 1748 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Robert Bennett's account with Thomas Cresap, 1748-1749 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jeremiah Been's account with Thomas Cresap, 1749 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Arrest warrant for Thomas Cresap, debtor, May 11, 1750 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - William Anderson's account with Thomas Cresap, 1751 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Richard Pearis and Thomas Nixon's account with Thomas Cresap, 1751-1752 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Debts to Thomas Cresap, 1754-1760 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Debt of BomGardner to Lenox Scott, 1756 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Captain McDonald's account with Thomas Cresap, 1770 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Arrest warrant for Bryan Brian, debtor, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - William Sheppard's account with Thomas Cresap, March 3, 1745 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Adam Stephen, 1751-1791; VI.
  Adam Stephen (ca.1721-1791) was born in Scotland, and educated as a surgeon. He served as a physician with the British Navy in Jamaica before traveling to Virginia in 1748 where he worked as a doctor and planter. He temporarily commanded the Virginia militia in the French and Indian War, and attained the rank of brigadier general in the Continental Army before his dismissal in 1777. It is unclear if Stephen was a member or a client of the Ohio Company. The series includes documentation of Adam Stephen's debts to others and materials related to his work as physician.
  - Materials related to Adam Stephen's work as physician, 1751-1752 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to William Minter, March 27, 1754 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - G. Fairfax's account with Gershom Keyes, 1761-1762 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to John Graham, May 4, 1764 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to Van Swearingen, October 2, 1764 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to John Mangy, 1764-1765 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Debts witnessed by Adam Stephen, 1764-1766 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to Joseph Beeler, April 26, 1765 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Richard Ragon's debt to Adam Stephen, 1765 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Adam Stephens vs. John Stewart, 1768-1791 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Adam Stephens debt to James Wood, September 5, 1769 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Agreement between Adam Stephen and C. W. Smith, November 19, 1770 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Deposition of Elizabeth Clark, February 25, 1771 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hite vs. Shays, 1771 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - [Aminadab] Seekright vs. Ferdinand Deadnought, 1771 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Related to horses stolen from Adam Stephen, 1771 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Adam Stephen vs. Moses Keywood, March 1772 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to Lewis Neill, December 15, 1772 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Adam Stephen and James Kieth's debt to John Ewing, December 6, 1773 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Phillip Pendleton's debt to Adam Stephens, Nov 10, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Adam Stephen vs. Jas. Keith, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to John Shover, July 26, 1786 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Joseph Vaneer's debt to Adam Stephen, November 1791 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Adam Stephen's debt to Alexander Cunningham, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - John Dougherty's account with Adam Stephens, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Stite vs. Adam Stephens, 1773 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- William Crawford, 1757-1789; VII.
  William Crawford (1732-1782) was a soldier and surveyor who mentored under George Washington. Crawford served on the frontier at Fort Pitt, and later commanded the ill-fated Crawford Expedition into the Ohio territory, after which he was executed following his capture by the Delaware. William and his brother, Valentine Crawford, were members of the Ohio Company.
  - William Crawford's debt to Thomas Cresap, June 3, 1757 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - William Crawford's debt to John Greenfield, September, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - William Crawford's account with John Dow, 1756-1758 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - William Crawford's debt to Nathaniel Thomas, June 26, 1760 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - William Crawford's account with John Stanton, January 7, 1762 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Valentine Crawford's debt to David Shepherd, September 9, 1762 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - William Crawford's account with John Brigg, November 4, 1771 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Memorandum of William Crawford's debt to the Crown, July 23, 1772 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - William Crawford's promise to repay Fielding Lewis, August 27, 1772 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - George Roote's account with Dorsey Pentecost, 1779-1780 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - William Crawford, debt (fragments), December 16, 1789 (Box 3, Folder 62)
- General Debt Notes and Correspondence, 1736-1793; VIII.
  This series contains manuscripts documenting debts peripherally related to the Ohio Company's trade in goods and role as money lender. Notable persons represented include James Craik (1730-1814), a close friend and personal physician to George Washington, and James Wood (1707-1759), father of James Wood, Jr., Governor of Virginia. Also present are field notes on the Charlottesburg Survey. In one of the few letters in this series, John Stuart mentions uneasiness with the Cherokees to Lord Botetourt, the colonial Governor of Virginia.
  - Thomas Baleh's debt to Elizabeth Martin, May 5, 1736 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - James Routledge's debt to Robert Wilson, November 17, 1741 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - John Nelon's debt to Richard Lowdon (2 copies), July 7, 1742 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - William Levy and Daniel Neil's debt to Edward Charlston, July 26, 1743 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Daniel Neale's debt to Edward Charleton, July 29, 1743 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Joseph Robin's debt to Burr Harrison, February 13, 1744 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - John Smith and Robert Worthington's debt to Thomas Hunt, March 9, 1744 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - James Rutledge's promise to repay William Mitchell, September 7, 1745 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Hugh Parker's debt to Nicholas [Van Imans], October 15, 1745 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Arrest warrant for debtor [name illegible], 1745 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Patrick Matthew's debt to Joseph Thompson, October 14, 1746 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - David Lloyd's debt to [James] Sheppard, May 22, 1746 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Gavin Black's debt to Jacob [Wiss], September 29, 1746 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Payment to Thomas Chester, 1746 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - John Corry's debt to James Lemon, 1746 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - John [Doone's] debt to William Mattherson, May 11, 1747 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - William Greene's debt to Benjamin [Penneya], May 20, 1747 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Joseph Carrell's debt to Hanah Humphrey, March 8, 1748 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Archibald Craig and John Hardin's debt to John Hopes, October 1748 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Samuel Walker's debt to Hugh Parker, 1748-1749 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - L. Worthington's debt to Hugh Parker, April 7, 1749 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Thomas Caton's debt to Thomas Walker, Nov. 10, 1755 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Thomas Caton's debt to Peacock Bigger, April 26, 1749 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Andrew Bowman's account, 1749 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - William May's debt to James [Hude], November 11, 1749 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - John Moss's debt to John Woodfin, April 5, 1750 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Hugh Parker's account with the Ohio Company, July 1750 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Henry Netherton's debt to Robert Rae and William Green, August 17, 1750 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - John Rain's debt to William Hoge, August 17, 1750 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Samuel Flower's account with James Jones, 1750 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Grand jury summons for Andrew Campbell (copy), May 15, 1751 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Jeremiah Claud's account with William Boyle, August 22, 1751 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Nicholas Zechan's debt to Abraham Levar, Jr., October 7, 1751 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - George [Hoge] and Jospeh Staton's debt to Roger and Jasper Sutton, May 29, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - William Quinton's debt to Andrew Ross and Well Cunningham, May 30, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Richard Moore's debt to Francise Hall, June 27, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Thomas Hooper's debt to Robert and Thomas [Duncors], November 28, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - John Huston's payment to Lawrence Stevens, July 18, 1753 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Robert Mossely and Murtah Handley's debt to Merideth Helm, September 20, 1753 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Debt to William Harris, November 19, 1753 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Transfer of account from Hugh O'Kelly to Henry VanMetor, February 26, 1754 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - James Leith's debt to William Wist, December 14, 1754 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - James Catlet's account with Robert Carter, 1754-6 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Thomas Hampton's debt to Allan Macrae, March 15, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Simeon Rice's debt to Ramsay and Dixon, June 2, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Andrew Crawford and Thomas Spencer's debt to William Cochran, Jun 19, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - William Campbell's debt to Nicholas Mercer, June 2, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - David Gelgood and William Vancee's debt to Samuel and Andrew Blackburn, August 18, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Robert Mosely's debt to Gabriel Jones and Lewis Neil, October 6, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Daniel Wilson's debt to Maxwell Guthrie & Co., 1755 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Robert Carter's account with John Wood, 1756 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - William Roberts payment to [illegible] Harrison, March 7, 1758 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Peter McKeen's debt to Hester Hollis, April 2, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - William Frogg's debt to Wallon [Cauders], July 23, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Henry Heth's debt to Andrew [Sukis], September 29, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - John [Brickhard's debt to Peter [Virr], November 9, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Adam Destiny and Jacob Miller's debt to James Crase, May 16, 1760 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - John Hardin and James Wood's debt to [Dansill Prosilly], August 7, 1760 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Robert Gain's account with Cunningham, Stewart & Co., October 1760 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - John Stewart's promise to repay Van Swearingen, November 27, 1760 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Enoch Nash's debt to John Wikoff, April 3, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Adam Derting vs. James Creass, June 4, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Davys Colmer's debt to James Craik, December 3, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - William Ramsay vs John Stewart, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Stephen Bowling and William Claiman's debt to Joseph Pack, 1764 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Thomas Caton's debt to Arthur Charleton, October 21, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - G. L. Hockheimer's debt to Eberhard Daring, February 3, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Simeon Hiett's debt to William Lochry, June 1, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Stephen Rawling's promise to repay Richard Pearis, June 12, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Arrest warrant for Elijah Isaacs, August 12, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Samuel Mason and Jonathan Clark's debt to John Bozworth, September 5, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - William Fowler's account with William Cochran, November 4, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Henry Heinzman's payment to Mr. Price, November 24, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - John Hardin's account with Greenfield, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Jacob Shife vs. Joseph Shetanawer's, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Frederick and Mary Hufman's promise to repay Frederick [Insult], August 29, 1763 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Notes on the Charlottesburg Survey [LM p165-166], ca. 1763 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - John Ord and Thomas Rutherford's debt to Gabriel Jones, May 8, 1764 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Henry Brinker & Co. vs. Benjamin [Grubblate], August 13, 1764 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Thomas Benfield's debt to William and Ramsay Carlyle, August 31, 1764 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Lawrence Trapp vs. John Funks, January 4, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Richard Pearin vs. Franci Maginnis, January 22, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Land indenture from Ja. Kieth to Burr Harrison and Angus McDonald, March 5, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - John Lehen's debt to J. Wood, June 2, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Thomas Waddlington's appointment as attorney for William and Gina Waddlington, August 17, 1767 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - John Randolph's promise to repay [Bondom] Fairfax, September 24, 1767 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Robert Rutherford's debt to John Marshall, November 7, 1767 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Land indenture from Luke Collins to Joseph Watson, November 8, 1767 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Bryan Brown's debt to Owen Jones, March 5, 1768 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - McCormack vs. Reagan, 1768 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Robert Rutherford's debt to Andrew Cochran, William Cunningham & Co., 1768 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Cornelius Livingston's debt to David Ker, January 6, 1769 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Land indenture from John and Sarah Allan to James Gibson, Mar 11, 1769 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - John Ord's debt to Thomas Rutherford, August 1, 1769 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Land indenture from Prudence Harbor to Jacob Vandeveer, September 2, 1769 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - James Walpole's notes to John Hanbury [LM p371], February 17, 1770 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - John Stuart to Lord Botetourt, April 27, 1770 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - John Normster to James Craik, January 12, 1791 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - John Wormely's account with James Craik, January 14, 1791 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Richard Crunk's debt to Edward Brown, March 22, 1742 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Unidentified fragment 1, undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Unidentified fragments, J. Sullivan's debt, 1754 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Debt to Joseph Hobbs, 1743 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Washington letter (copy), 1754 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - J. Sullivan's debt to unknown (fragment), 1754 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Sam Young, fragments, undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - William Stephen and John Stevenson's debt to Thomas Connelly, undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Arrest warrant for James Huston (copy), 1954 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - William Stephen's debt to Thomas Connelly, undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
- Manuscript Copies of Papers Relating to The Ohio Company of Virginia, 1747-1749; IX.
  This volume contains manuscript copies of correspondence between 1747 and 1749, copied from the Records of the Board of Trade, involving the colonial Governor of Virginia Sir William Gooch, the Board of Trade in London, and others. William Darlington commissioned this copy in January of 1870. The letters in this volume discuss the creation, justification for, and financing of the Ohio Company. They reflect the urgency of the British to colonize the Ohio territory before the French in order to increase trade with American Indians, and to obtain access to valuable natural resources. The majority of the letters are accompanied with a scope note on either the page following the letter or the page directly before the letter, written by the copyist.
  - Manuscript Copies of Papers Relating to The Ohio Land Company of Virginia, 1747-1749 (Box 4, Folder 88)